hey what's up guys my name is the chana
and welcome back to my state boss boss
series today we're going to be talking
all about dynamic array since a boss
boss specifically the standard vector
class so now that we're finally
beginning to write some courtesy bus
boss is very important that we get
accustomed to C++ a standard library or
in this case something called a standard
template library
now the Santas template library is
essentially a library filled with
containers container types right things
that contain certain daughter and is
called a standard template library
because you can template it into
anything the whole average templated
meaning that the underlying data type of
the container so in other words the data
type that the container contains that is
actually up to you to decide the whole
things made out of templates which
reminds me we need to talk about
templates and we will very soon
templates are a huge topic so we'll kind
of divide it from beginning to advanced
kind of templates as we go along but
essentially all you need to know to use
that you don't need to know anything
about templates to actually use the
senate template library all you need to
know is that you can provide the
underlying data type that this data
structure actually handles and that's
pretty cool it makes it very versatile
and it means that you don't have to
resort to write in your own data
structures or anything like that so a
bus Clause provides us with a class
called a vector and that vector is in
the STD namespace
now it's called better that's the first
problem
why is it called a vector well there's
actually a story behind that I've linked
as like an article or Wikipedia page in
the description that will actually talk
about that but it shouldn't be called
vector it should be called something
like ArrayList because that makes a lot
more sense is essentially a dynamic or
dynamic array but not vector vectors a
very weird name for this and a lot of
people who first kind of get into C++
really get confused about what honor
this vector thing isn't is it a
mathematical vector no no it's it's just
it's kind of like a set it's a set that
doesn't enforce any kind of uniqueness
to its actual elements so in other words
it's basically an array but unlike the
normal array types in in C++ either just
raw arrays or the standard array class
which we might which we actually did
mention in the arrays video if you guys
haven't seen that click up there but we
will probably have a dedicated video
about that as well unlike array this can
actually resize
means that when you create this vector
when you create this dynamic array it
doesn't have a set size you can give it
a set size and whatever if you want to
initialize a with a certain size but you
basically don't give it a size you just
create this vector or this array and
then you basically just put elements
into it and every time you put an
element into it the size grows so I can
start off not knowing how many elements
actually want in my array and then just
push ten things into it and suddenly I
have an array with ten items now two
people who kind of are new to
programming or new to computer science
might be like well how does that work
how could how is it possible to just
have an array that resizes and we're
actually going to over the course of
this simple spice series we're actually
going to be rewriting a lot of these
data structures that because they're
sensitive waswas ourselves and in a lot
of cases we're actually gonna optimize
them and make them a lot faster than the
ones in the standard template library
because this one's on the sentient
template library aren't especially fast
that's not really the priority of them
and so in a lot of cases studios and
teams end up actually creating their own
container libraries in example I work at
AAA so an example is we use something
called EA STL there's a link to that in
the description below it's on github you
can look at the source code that's one
example of something that is actually
usually in most cases a lot faster than
the stuff that's actually in a standard
template library anyway I'm getting a
little bit ahead of myself here um the
point is that the way that Santa vectors
actually work we'll talk about that more
in more detail in a future video
however the gist of it is that basically
when you exceed the size that is
allocated so when you make a vector it
might allocate like ten elements for
example or enough memory for ten
elements when you exceed that it
basically creates a new array in memory
that's bigger than the first one copies
everything to there and then deletes the
old one and that way you suddenly just
have basically a new array as somewhere
else in memory that has a lot more
storage and you can keep adding things
to it like that in practice it actually
tends to allocate quite often and isn't
the best performance wise unless you set
it up properly so this video is just
going to be for beginners who don't know
what what this vector thing is how you
can use it and all that and then
I think the next video after this one
we're actually going to talk about
specifically how we can use the standard
vector in an optimal way and that will
kind of get into some more advanced
things so if you want to check that
video out if you already know how back
to works and you wanna waste your time
watching this video click on the link
right there and that will take you to
the advanced I guess video and we'll
talk about how we can optimize our usage
of the vector class but for now let's
create a dynamic array so what I've got
over here is a basics dropped here
there's the vertex this is specifically
a vertex position I should add as you
can see it's got x y&z this is just a
dummy class it really could be anything
I've also written an output operator
over here just so that we can print this
easily to the console if we want to make
an actual static array of this we would
kind of have two choices right ignoring
the standard array class we could just
create a static array which might have
five elements in it but this way we're
kind of getting tied to the size and
even if we do allocated on the heap like
sorry you can see that we're kind of
still tied to this size and we've kind
of allocated five vertices which means
that we can access zero through four
again if you're not sure how arrays work
definitely check out that video first
but we can access the index 0 through 4
and then if we try and go higher we get
run into a problem and sometimes that's
just not good enough because we want to
keep adding vertices for example we
might have a program where we allow the
user to enter in data we don't really
want to stop the user after I don't know
maybe ten vertices or something I say
sorry you can't enter any more if we
want to keep that going we need a way to
say that when you've reached them that
max capacity resized get bigger so that
you can store more data another solution
to this problem is kind of allocating an
absurd amount of vertices and then
basically just saying that's the hard
limit for the program anything above
that is ridiculous we're never going to
hit that anyway so basically this
program does support unlimited vertices
in a way but of course that's also not
ideal because it means that you're using
all of that memory whereas if if we only
have five vertices that's a huge waste
so what we can do instead is use the
vector class I'm going to include vector
over here and then I'm going to go ahead
and make one so the way that we make one
is we type in STD vector then we specify
the type now this type is just a C++
type of what what is actually going to
be in the array so in our case we want
vertices so we'll type in a vertex now
call this vertices just like that and
that's it we're done now it's worth
noting that unlike languages like Java
where you cannot pass primitive types in
here this is a C++ template so you can
pass primitive types in here I can type
int like this or float like that in Java
we would actually have to use the
integer class or something like that but
this is very similar to C sharp as well
where we don't actually have to specify
the class type we can just specify the
raw type the primitive type someone
change this back to vertex now note that
I'm not storing a bunch of pointers to
the vertex to vertex structs right I'm
actually to storing vertices just vertex
U just in line and there's actually a
big difference between that a lot of
people tend to ask should I be storing
pointers to heap allocated classes in my
vector or should I be storing stack
allocated basically in line allocated
like vertex classes or vertex structs
and the answer that is it depends it
really does depend I think I'm gonna
make a video in the future that will
talk about this specific problem in more
detail because for a lot of people it's
it is hard to decide whether you should
be using like vertex pointers in this
case or just vertex objects right
there's a big difference the primary
consideration is that it is technically
more optimal to store vertex objects
instead of pointers because if you solve
vertex objects your memory is going to
be in line dynamic arrays are arrays in
the sense that their memory is
contiguous which means that it's not
fragmented in in memory right it's all
just in a row and if you store vertex
objects in line like this you've
literally got one in vertex XYZ XYZ XYZ
XYZ one after the other and that's
really really optimal if you actually
want to iterate over them and set all
the more changes that won't read all of
them or whatever it is that you want to
do with them because they're likely
going to well they are all going to be
on the same cache line in that sense I
know I said beat you know I'm already
talking about cache lines and stuff
we're gonna get into this in the future
but basically you want to try if it's at
all possible try and allocate the main
line like this the only problem with
this is that if it comes time to
actually resize the vector it needs to
copy all that data and if you
happen to have something like a vector
of strings and you're going to be
resizing that vector often and it does
need to reallocate and recopy everything
that could potentially be a very slow
operation whereas with pointers the
actual memory stays intact because
you're just holding pointers to that
memory right so the actual memory stays
intact but then when it comes time to
resize it just copies those integers
which are the memory addresses to the
actual data and the data is still stored
just in various places in memory so it
is it is a bit of a hard decision and I
don't really want to get into it too
much now but that should just give you
kind of the gist of this try and keep
the muscle objects if if possible
pointers are kind of always as with
stack allocation heap allocation
pointers are always kind of your last
resort if you really really need need to
actually do it that way
so now that I bought this how do I add
stuff to it well it's very simple you
just type in vertices don't push back
and other languages is called a door and
then C++ the same operation is called
push back and then you basically push
back at that text so in this case that I
have a constructor but I could just use
and initialize a list like this to
specify my x y&z so I'll say 1 2 3 and
then I'll push another one back and
we'll write 4 5 6 ok pretty basic stuff
now let's iterate through all these and
print them so in an array we don't know
in it oh I should say in the C style
array we don't actually know the size of
the array but in this case of course
since vector as a full class and
everything we actually do know the size
and we can ask it
so let's write a for loop and we'll ride
eyes less than vertices dot size that's
the function that we used to retrieving
the size and then I'll just say sta C
out vertices and then we can use the
index operator to access in Java we have
to use get because Java reports us to
have operator overloading but it was
very much like c-sharp has overloaded
the index operator so that we can
actually just type it in like that as if
it was just any array which is which is
nice so if we hit a five-round run our
code you can see that we get 1 2 3 4 5 6
which is perfect we can also use range
based for loops with this so instead of
writing all this code we could rewrite
this for loop like this which is going
to look much simpler we'll just say for
vertex V then column them
the vector which is vertices we can just
print V like this and if we hit at five
you can see that we get the exact same
result pretty twice now in this specific
example because I've written vertex like
this this is actually going to be
copying each vertex into the scope of
this for loop we don't want to do that
we want to avoid copying wherever
possible so if we just stick a simple
ampersand over here like this or maybe
even marketers Const it doesn't really
matter as long as you've got the
ampersand here to make it a reference
it's not going to copy the data if we
run this we will get the same result
however we're not just needlessly
copying vertices finally if we want to
clear the list of vertices we just type
in vertices clear that will set the
array size back to zero we can also
remove vertices individually just by
doing the vertices dot arrays and then
with this now now I just I love C++
because of this look at look at this to
someone who's new to say boss boss
looking at this actual function
signature it's like what is going on and
even me right now reading this after so
many years it's like what's up I know
this is why a lot of people hate it but
what's not very beginner friendly but if
we if we read this it does make sense
arrays returns a vector iterator so we
can kind of we're gonna kind of just
ignore all that return type this is the
erase function and over here you can see
takes a constant iterative okay what
that means is that we can't just right
there raised to or something like that
we actually have to take an iterator now
if we want to specifically remove for
example the second element which is an
index one what we can actually do is
take in the beginning of vertices by
typing in vertices of begin and then
just add one to it and then that will
actually erase that second element so if
we move this followed down here after
the arrays to see what happens you can
see in this case we do actually erase
that second element and everything's
great another thing that I'll mention is
that when you are actually passing these
vectors into into functions or into
classes or whatever you really do want
to make sure that you're passing them by
reference okay if you're not going to be
modifying it than by constants just like
this because by doing that you're
ensuring you're not copying that entire
array into this function so make sure
that when you do stuff like this you
actually do pass it by reference like
that okay very important stuff okay I
think that's pretty much it for a basic
overview of the vector class
dynamic arrays in C++ and how you can
use them in the next video we're going
to really get in-depth and talk about
optimization about how we can avoid
reallocations how we can avoid copying
and all that stuff and probably some
other tips and tricks with vectors in
general for people who already kind of
get the general premise and want to
actually know how they can optimize
their code this way though the way that
I've shown you over here with like
pushback and just this kind of workflow
that's probably what you'll see most of
the time there's nothing really wrong
with it vectors specifically aren't that
slaughter usually but in some cases of
course we do want to squeeze out just
every bit of performance that we
possibly can and that's what the next
video is going to be about do you guys
enjoyed the video don't forget to hit
the like button you can also support me
on patreon by going to patreon or conv
watch the channel you'll be able to see
videos early contribute to the planning
of videos as well as another pretty cool
rewards which you can check out on that
side thank you guys for watching as
always I'll see you next time goodbye
[Music]